Finding Aid for Janet D. Lynn Papers 1970-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Janet D. Lynn Papers
1970-1998
1972-1987
Lynn, Janet D.
Janet Lynn, founder of the Citizens Council for Land Use Research and Education (CLURE), was an activist and environmentalist in southeastern Michigan. The collection documents CLURE's involvement with controversial land issues such as the construction of highways and shopping centers, as well as its efforts to educate the public about issues of land use and planning.
921100 Aa 2
3.7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated in two accessions by Janet D. Lynn (Donor No. 7969 ) in September 1991 and October 2002.
The collection is open for research.
Janet D. Lynn, a land use activist from West Bloomfield, Michigan, founded the Citizens Council for Land Use Research and Education, Inc. (CLURE) in 1971, in response to her concern that the natural richness of West Bloomfield Township might be destroyed. The voluntary organization was formed following a private effort to offer community planning services to municipalities in southeastern Michigan. Lynn has served as both president and executive vice president of the organization.
CLURE was organized with three goals in mind: to educate the public about the nature of the land use decision-making process; to promote the need for reforms in the public interest; and to encourage citizen participation in land-use planning. CLURE has supplied citizens with leadership, information and educational programs related to projected effects of proposed land use changes on the community. The programs have also encompassed conferences and symposia dealing with generic problems of land in American society. Members of CLURE have served on advisory councils of the Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG) as well as other special task forces.
Two of CLURE'S biggest projects dealt with the consequences of a vast proposed regional shopping center in a nationally reported "demonstration project" and a request for performance of an environmental impact statement on an expressway extension.
A proposed expressway project was first suggested in 1929. In 1970, Lynn discovered that the federal government required an impact statement when federal funds were to be used for a large project and that there was an order from Michigan's Governor William Milliken that impact statements be written for projects using state funds. CLURE requested a statement from the Michigan Department of Highways and Transportation, sued the state to halt acquisition of right-of-way property for the expressway, and requested that public hearings be held on the matter. In the summer of 1973, Milliken ordered an environmental impact statement be performed and the State House of Representatives committee began investigating the need for the expressway. As a result of Lynn's efforts, the federal Department of Transportation ordered the state to write another impact statement. With the addition of two new state highway commissioners who were more sympathetic to CLURE's position, the Commission, in 1977, ordered the highway department to stop construction of the expressway.
Following these successful projects, Lynn continued to be an advocate for responsible planning and use of land through CLURE's involvement with local towns and organizations in Oakland County, Michigan and its sponsorship of symposia exploring broader issues of land use in the United States.
The Janet D. Lynn Papers (3.7 linear feet) document CLURE's activities in land use activism and education. These include the Northwestern Highway Extension project and the related M-275 freeway discussions, efforts to stop construction of proposed shopping centers in West Bloomfield and Novi, Michigan, as well as discussion of legislation in the state of Michigan and materials related to CLURE-sponsored symposia. In addition to these topics, the records also document CLURE itself, through legal, promotional and fundraising materials.
The collection is arranged in three series: Biographical/Historical Information, Northwestern Highway Extension, 1972-1981 and Citizens Council for Land Use Research and Education (CLURE) Records.
Subjects:
Social action--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Citizens Council for Land Use Research and Education.; Highway planning--Michigan--Citizen participation.; Land use--Michigan.; Lynn, Janet D.; Novi (Mich.); Shopping centers.; West Bloomfield (Mich.: Township)
- Biographical/Historical Information
  The collection begins with a small series of Biographical/Historical Information that will provide the researcher with an overview of the issues involved in the highway and shopping center projects.
  - General (Box 1)
- Northwestern Highway Extension, 1972-1981
  Northwestern Highway Extension, 1972-1981 (1.2 linear feet) contains correspondence, arranged chronologically, with various agencies involved with the project, including SEMCOG, Michigan State Highway Commission and the federal Department of Transportation. There is also an extensive collection of newspaper clippings that document the highway projects. The bulk of the clippings deal with Northwestern Highway and can be found in the chronological folders, 1973-1980. Two bound collections of minutes from the public hearing of the Special Committee to Study the Northwestern Highway Extension, August and September 1973, are useful as well.
  - Bond Issue, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Citizens Advisory Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - General Information, 1972-1981; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan State Highway Commission, 1970-1978
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Publications (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1973-1988; 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Northwestern Coalition, 1972-1980
    - M-275, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    - Northwestern Highway, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Southeastern Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG), 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Special House Committee to Study the Northwestern Highway Extension, 1973
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Minutes, August-September 1973 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, September 1973 (Box 2)
- Citizens Council for Land Use Research and Education (CLURE) Records
  Citizens Council for Land Use Research and Education (CLURE) Records (2.5 linear feet), the bulk of which date from 1971-1987, document the administration of CLURE as well as its activities. In order to facilitate use, arrangement of the files is somewhat artificial, with materials grouped into larger topics (e.g. Fundraising, Legislation and Other Organizations) whenever possible. Of particular interest are materials relating to the effort to halt construction of a shopping center in West Bloomfield, Michigan in 1973, information on various symposia sponsored by CLURE, and records of contacts and collaboration with other land use advocate organizations in Michigan. Also included are correspondence files, newspaper clippings and a variety of literature relating to land use and land use organizations, and promotional materials for CLURE. Administrative material includes legal documentation (bylaws and articles of incorporation) and information about the advisory board and board of directors (meetings and correspondence).
  - CLURE background
    - Annual reports to Michigan Department of Commerce, 1975-1985 (Box 2)
    - Ongoing projects, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Prospectus, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Advisory board, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors
    - General, 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - Meetings
      - 1972-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1977-1985 (Box 2)
      - 1986 (Box 2)
    - Memos, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Brighton, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Center for Applied Land Use Research and Education, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Community service, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1981-1989 (Box 2)
      - 1969-1990 (Box 2)
    - Inquiries and assistance, 1973-1978 (Box 2)
    - Letters to the Editor, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
    - Beverly Cigler, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Joseph A. Dennis, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Protection Agency, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Wesley Gould, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Frank Popper, 1978-1988 (Box 2)
    - Brian Stanford, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
    - Roger Storm, 1991-1998 (Box 2)
    - William H. Whyte, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Detroit
    - Clippings, 1971-1989 (Box 2)
    - New Center-Lynn Associates METROSERV, 1966-1969; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Environmental action-State of Michigan, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Impact Statements, 1973-1974; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Fundraising
    - Charles Stewart Mott Foundation, 1976-1978; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Department of Health, Education & Welfare, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Ford Foundation, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - General, 1973; undated (Box 3)
    - Michigan Council for the Humanities, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Oakland County Grant Coordinator, 1975 (Box 3)
    - The Village Woman's Club, Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, 1978-1983 (Box 3)
  - Growth and development in Southeastern Michigan, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Land In America, 1976-1979 (Box 3)
  - Land Use Task Force, 1973 (Box 3)
    (See also Legislation: Mastin Land Use Bill)
  - Legal/Financial
    - Bylaws, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
    - Charitable Trust Registration Statement, 1974-1981 (Box 3)
    - IRS rulings, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Legal documentation & records, 1974-1991 (Box 3)
  - Legislation
    - Mastin Land Use Bill (H.B. 5055/6097), 1973-1974; 2 folders (Box 3)
      (See also Land Use Task Force)
    - Michigan courts, 1972-1975 (Box 3)
    - Michigan legislation, 1972-1974; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Proposed Legislation, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Lynn Associates METROSERV, 1971; undated (Box 3)
  - Maps, 1954-1985 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings and miscellaneous literature
    - General, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Land development in Southeast Michigan, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Southeastern Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG)-Transportation planning, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Oakland County Planning Commission, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Oakland Township, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
  - Orion Township, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
  - Other Organizations
    - Advance West Bloomfield, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Concerned Citizens for West Bloomfield (CCWB)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 3)
        (includes Northwestern Highway controversy)
      - 1984-1987 (Box 3)
        (includes Marshbank Park controversy)
    - Conservation Foundation, 1973 (Box 3)
    - East Michigan Environmental Action Council, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Massachusetts organizations, 1976 (Box 3)
      (includes MA Audubon Society, MA Tomorrow and League of Women Voters of MA)
    - Michigan Student Environmental Confederation, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - UAW (United Automobile, Aerospace & Agricultural Implement Workers of America), 1972 (Box 3)
    - West Bloomfield Land Conservancy, 1980 (Box 3)
    - West Bloomfield Land Conservancy Committee, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - West Bloomfield Natural Resources Committee, 1976 (Box 3)
    - West Bloomfield Parks & Recreation Committee, 1971 (Box 3)
    - West Bloomfield Senior Foundation, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1980 (Box 3)
  - Promotion
    - General, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1972-1974 (Box 4)
    - Draft letters, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Press releases, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Property tax, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - "Region", 1972 (Box 4)
  - School for Citizens, undated (Box 4)
  - Shopping centers
    - Novi, Michigan, 1973 (Box 4)
    - West Bloomfield, Michigan, 1972-1973
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  - Solid waster, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
  - Southfield, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Special Commission on Land Use, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Symposia
    - Brochures, 1972-1983 (Box 4)
    - "Autos, Robots and Land Use", 1982 (Box 4)
    - "Do the Laws Secure Our Land?", 1972 (Box 4)
    - "Economic Crisis & Political Response in the Auto City: Detroit & Turin", 1981 (Box 4)
    - "The Face of America: Land Use in the Year 2000", 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - Land Trusts Conference, 1979-1987 (Box 4)
    - "Money, Politics & Land: The Challenge to Communities"
      - Council on Environmental Quality, 1990 (Box 4)
      - Preparatory materials, 1985-1989 (Box 4)
      - Program information, 1990 (Box 4)
    - "Shaping Our Future: Foundations for Community Initiatives", 1979 (Box 4)
  - "This Land", 1972-1975 (Box 4)
    (CLURE newsletter)
  - Transportation
    - Department of State Highways, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Freeways, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Urban Land Institute, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Washington, D.C., 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    (includes Environmental Protection Agency, Council on Environmental Quality, Department of Transportation)
  - West Bloomfield
    - 1970-1975 (Box 4)
    - 1983 (Box 4)
    - Bauervic proposal, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Hospital, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Land trusts, circa 1978 (Box 4)
    - Shopping center, 1973 (Box 4)
  - White House Conference on Balanced National Growth and Economic Development, 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - William H. Whyte, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Yonkers, New York-Regional Shopping Center, 1973 (Box 4)
    (See also Correspondence: Inquiries and assistance)
  - Miscellaneous, 1974-1985 (Box 4)